Can everybody hear me?
>> We hear you, sir.
We'll wait a few seconds till we have
100 students here.
Hope they're taking the time.
Okay. Good morning everybody and uh
welcome to this for third lecture in our
series of lectures on convolutional
neural networks.
So here's a quick outline. We're going
to go through a quick recap of CNN's and
then we're going to discuss back
propagation through CNN's. The grade out
topics are topics that we will discuss
in the next lecture.
So the story so far is that pattern
classification tasks such as does this
picture contain a cat or does this
recording include the word hello are
best performed by scanning for the
target pattern. Scanning an input with a
network and combining the outcomes is
equivalent to scanning with individual
neurons hierarchically. So the first
level neurons would scan the input.
Higher level neurons would scan the maps
formed by the lower level neurons and a
final decision unit or layer makes the
final decision. Defformations in the
input can be handled by pooling. For
two-dimensional or higher dimensional
scans, this structure is called a
convolutional neural network. For a 1D
scan along time, it's called a 1D CNN or
alternately a time delay neural neural
network. So does everybody remember all
this? Just give me a yes. I'll move on.
All of this familiar.
Okay, I have a single yes. So I'll take
that for communal yes. Right. So here's
how the whole thing works. Uh the
general architecture of a convolutional
neural network was as follows. You had
several convolution layers. Within each
convolutional layer, you had several
maps where each map
uh identified or detected a specific
feature at various locations in their
input. Then you had pooling layers where
the pooling operations operated on the
uh map uh map wise on the input maps to
introduce some jitter and variance. So
here's what the convolution layer look
like.
In a convolution layer, you have two
stages of operation. First, each map in
the convolution layer is computed from
all of the maps in the previous layer.
And the computation first results in an
aphine map which is obtained by
convolving a filter over the maps in the
previous layer and then we apply an
activation function element wise on this
aphine map to produce an activation map.
So how was the aphine map itself
computed? For every one of the output
maps that we wanted to compute,
we had a filter and the filter in turn
had as many channels or planes as the
number of input maps. So we said that we
also mentioned that maps are alternately
called channels. So I'm going to use the
term channel. So we have as many filters
as the number of output channels we
desire. Each and each output channel has
a corresponding filter. And the filter
itself has as many channels as the
number of input channels. And the way we
computed the uh output aine map we did
it using the corresponding filter. We
place the filter on the set of input
maps. Again remember that the filter has
as many channels as the number of input
channels. So when you place the filter
on the input channels, one channel of
the filters sits at top each one of the
input channels. And then we compute an
inner product which is basically uh an
elementwise product of the filter
elements with the value underneath which
we then sum up and that gives you the
aphine map at one location. So this
operation is performed while scanning
the input with the filter to get the
output fine map. Again uh one filter
gives you only one fine map. So if you
want multiple uh aine maps you would
need multiple filters. Then to compute
the activation map we applied an
activation function element wise on the
aine map. And this was the final output
of the convolution layer.
So more explicitly
uh here is the set of all dependencies.
Every one of the input channels is
involved in the computation of every one
of the output channels or the output
aine maps. Each aphine map is locally uh
involved in the corres in the
computation of the corresponding
activation map. So all input channels
influence every one of the aine maps.
each input a each aphine map only
influences the corresponding activation
map. So if you were so actually let's
have our first poll.
Wait. So sorry the polls are not up.
What happened? I'm sorry.
Sorry guys. These are the wrong polls.
Please, I'm going to skip this. Why are
the polls not up?
>> Um, bro, let me look into it real quick.
The poll should have been up yesterday.
>> The polls are not up.
>> Okay, guys. I apologize.
>> We have forgotten to set up the
>> are interruptions. Let's go. Right. So,
can somebody please answer these? Uh,
anybody want to answer the question over
here? Uh the uh select all true
statements about a convolution layer. Is
the first statement true or false? The
number of channels in any filter equals
the number of input maps. True or false?
True. The number of channels in any
filter equals the number of output maps.
True or false? False. Okay. The number
of filters equals the number of input
maps. True or false?
The third. And the fourth one, the
number of filters equals the number of
output maps.
Okay, so the first and the fourth,
right?
All right. So that was the convolution
layer. What about the pooling layer? The
pooling layer introduced jitter
invariance. We had a little pooling
filter which looked at a little region
of the input and picked the if you were
performing max pooling it picked the
largest value and just scan the input
picking the largest value at each point.
So this was the pseudo code for the
pooling the max pooling the way we did
it at each within each region you just
picked up the index of the largest value
and then copied the value over.
Alternately, we saw we could perform
mean pooling. We would just where we
would just compute the mean of all the
values in the region and then we'd scan.
So here was the pseudo code for the mean
pool, right? And so this was the the
totality of convolution and pooling.
We also had resampling layers. We can
proportionately decrease or increase the
size of maps by dropping or inserting
zeros. For down sampling, you drop sus
one rows or columns between rows and
columns. For upsampling, we insert sus
one rows or rows or columns of zeros
between adjacent entries. So this was
down sampling. If you wanted to down
sample by two, you basically masked out
every second row and every second column
and only retain the rest.
And in if you wanted to increase the
size of the map say by a factor of two,
you just introduced a row and a a column
of zeros between adjacent rows and
adjacent columns.
We also saw that in practice
we don't actually separately perform
convolution and downsampling or pooling
and downsampling. Instead we perform
convolution or pooling with a stride uh
which the stride accounts for the down
sampling. So also in the case of
upsampling
in the case of upsampling you actually
generally do introduce zeros and then
perform a convolution
and upsampling is always followed by
convolution layer. No other operation
makes sense. So upsampling is not useful
as the final layer of a CNN. You'll just
have a bunch of zeros. And we also saw
that when we have upsampling followed by
convolution, we like to call it
convolution with this uh
uh with a stride, right? Doesn't this
lead to unnecessary computation for
downsampling? You're just going to
you're just going to convolve with a
stride. So you're not going to be
computing any anything unnecessary.
Whereas if you split the operation into
two, you won't have unnecessary
computation. That answer Edward?
So moving on,
here is the summary.
When you have pooling with down
sampling,
uh you just merge these two into pooling
with a stride. Convolution followed by
down sampling. The two operations are
merged into convolution with a stride.
Upsampling followed by convolution. They
are actually two separate operations,
but you like we like to think of it as
convolution with a fractional stride.
So then a recap of the whole operation.
If you were to perform an image
classification task on images, the input
would be an image with three different
colors. They form three channels. Then
you'd have a series of convolution and
pooling operations where the filters for
convolutions would be cuboids. Pooling
is going to perform operate mapwise on
each map to with say max or mean pooling
and the out and typically pooling is
combined with downsampling. So pooling
is performed with a stride and then the
final layer the output of the final
layer is flattened and that's passed
through an MLP which computes the output
of the CNN. That's the entire operation.
So the learnable parameters are all of
these filters and the parameters of the
final MLP.
So how do we train the network? Training
is as in the case of a regular MLP.
The only difference is in the structure
of the network. We provide training
examples of images and their classes. If
you're performing, if you're training an
image classifier,
we define a loss which is a divergence
between the desired output and the true
output of the network in response to any
input.
The loss aggregates the divergence
divergences of the training set. Network
parameters are trained to minimize the
loss through variance of gradient
descent and gradients are computed using
back propagation.
So the way you define the loss for a
single training instance, you pass the
training instance through the entire
network. It's going to give you class
probabilities for all of your classes.
You have your desired output which is
typically one hot with a one for the
true class and zero for everything else.
You define a divergence between the two
typically across entropy loss which is
the same as a km divergence. And then
the so so this is what it would be right
given a training set of input output
pairs.
The divergence on the i instance is
going to be the divergence between y i
which is the output of the network in
response to x i and d which is the
desired output of the network. The
average of these divergences is your
loss and the loss is a function only of
the network parameters
and you're going to minimize the loss
with respect to these parameters using
gradient descent. So
once again the training loss is the
average divergence over all the training
instances.
If you want to perform gradient descent,
you'll be computing the derivative of
the loss with respect to each of your
parameters, which is just the average of
the derivatives of the divergences for
the individual training instances with
respect to the parameter. And this guy
over here is what we need to compute.
And so that's what we'll focus on in
this class. How do you compute the
derivative of the divergence of the
network with respect to any individual
parameter?
So again
for the final MLP you can do this using
straight up rules of back propagation
that we know and that's going to finally
give you derivatives not only for the
for all of these weights. It's also
going to give you derivatives for this
set the inputs of the MLP. Now these
inputs were just flattened versions of
the final layer of the network. So we
can fold these derivatives back into the
same shape. And so now going back you
have derivatives
of the divergence of the network with
respect to all the elements of the final
layer of the convolution portion of the
network. Did this make sense what I just
said? Yes or no?
Did that make sense?
I have two yeses. Can I get a few more
yeses please before everyone? Okay. And
so then our problem here is going to be
how to move those derivatives further
back and learn the derivatives for all
of the filters network parameters. And
we need to make some adjustments here.
We'd have to comput consider the shared
computation of the convolution layers
and the specific computations within the
pooling layers. Let's see how this is
done. So there are two different things
we need to do. First we have to back
propagate derivatives through
convolution layers. Again because
because we can assume that we finally
have derivatives with respect to all of
these maps, all the elements of all
these maps. For a convolution layer, we
can assume that we have the derivative
of the divergence with respect to every
element of every activation map in the
layer. So in the forward pass of course
we used all the input channels and the
filters to compute all the output
activation aine maps and then from them
the activation maps and the backward
parts we would have first got the
derivatives of the divergence for these
activation maps and then we have to
figure out how to propagate them back to
get the derivatives for these aine maps
for these filters and finally to the
input of the in of the convolution
layer. So the assumption we already have
the derivatives with respect to the
elements of the maps output by the final
convolution or pooling layer which is
obtained as a result of back propagating
through through the flat NLP and maybe
going back through the network. So for
the convolution layers, we now have to
figure out how to compute the
derivatives with respect to the aphine
elements of the aphine maps from the
derivatives of the output activation
maps. And then furthermore, we have to
figure out how to compute the
derivatives of the divergence with
respect to the elements of the input
channels to the convolution layer input
maps and also with respect to the filter
parameters. Did this make sense what we
are saying here?
This statement makes sense to everybody.
Yes. No. Okay.
And
for the pooling layers again I can
assume I have the derivatives with
respect to the elements of all the maps
that are output by the pooling and we
have to figure out how to compute the
derivatives with respect to the inputs
to the pooling layer. Okay,
so to summarize, we already we assume
you already have the derivatives with
respect to the elements of the maps
output by the final convolution or
pooling layer obtained as a result of
back propagating through the flat MLP.
For the convolution layers, we now have
to figure out how to compute the
derivatives with so the output of the
convolution layer is going are going to
be these Y's. And so we have to figure
out how to compute the derivatives
for the Z's from the derivatives for the
Y's and then move these back and compute
the derivatives for the Y's of the
previous layer and the filter parameters
for the pooling layers. Given the output
derivatives for the output of the
pooling layer, we have to figure out how
to compute the derivatives for the input
of the pooling layer.
So let's see how we can do all of this.
Let's look at the convolution layer
first. Now within the convolution layer,
there are two steps. First given the
derivatives with respect to the y's, we
have to figure out how to compute the
derivatives with respect to the z's.
Let's see how that is done. Now again
here
the output of the actual convolution was
to give us an aine map which is just
obtained by scanning the input channels
with a filter.
Then we applied an activation function
pointwise on these on the elements of
this aphine map to get the activation
map. So each aphine map only influence
the corresponding activation map going
back. So the element in Z was operated
on by an activation function to give
you. So going back now if I'm computing
my derivatives I can assume I have my
derivatives for all the y's. So which
means that I have all the
uh dy the divergence power dy right and
now I must figure out how to compute the
derivatives for the z's
that's easy enough without looking at
the slides given that y equals an
activation function applied to z given
the derivative for y how would you
compute the derivative for z anybody?
without looking at the rest of the
slide. Can someone tell me
how would you do this?
Anyone
chain rule and what is the exact formula
you'd get?
Someone
what is the formula you would get?
Dependency derivative.
Come on guys, it's easier than that.
Someone
All right, let me just break the
suspense.
Yes, thank you, Edward. That's just
going to be the derivative
with respect to the element of Y times
the derivative of the activation
function that converted Z to Y. This is
the chain rule, right?
Yes or no?
Yes or no, guys? Yeah, that should not
have been a surprise, right? You should
have known this all along. And so that
means now I have the derivatives with
respect to all the elements of all of
these Z's. I now have to figure out how
to pass those derivatives back to
compute the derivatives for the filters
and the input channels.
So
again when you're back propagating
through an aphine map
in the forward aphine computation we
computed these aphine maps. Basically
when I compute an aine map for the L
layer it's I'm going to have a bunch of
channels output channels within each
output channel I have several positions
each of these is going to be computed
using all the channel all the positions
of all the channels of the input main
name main namely the L minus one layer
and the filters corresponding to the L
layer. So now given the derivatives with
respect to these Z's, I must figure out
how to compute the derivatives with
respect to these Y's and the filters. So
let's see how this goes. Right?
First, how do I compute the derivative
for the Y's given the derivative for the
Z? Let's look at this again. So during
the forward pass you had all of these
input channels and these input channels
were used to compute the aine maps.
We're assuming that back prop has given
us the derivatives of the divergence
with respect to all the elements of
these aine maps. So we have to figure
out how to move this derivative back to
here.
This illustration clear to everybody
exactly what we're trying to do. Anyone?
Is this clear?
Okay, that's a that's a very muted yes.
Okay, now to this do this we have to
consider all the dependencies right now
if you consider any particular output
aphine map. This output aphine map was
computed using the corresponding filter
and the filter had as this is so so the
L map used the L filter and the filter
had as many channels as the number of
input channels right and each channel of
the filter operated on the corresponding
input channel in computing this aine
map. So every one of the input channels
influence the output activation map
through the corresponding channel of the
filter used to compute this map.
So did this is this influence picture
making sense to everybody? Yes Bruno, we
will need it. Is this influence picture?
Okay. So if I look at it carefully,
every one of these input channels is
used in computing the
any each fi map. So if so just
simplifying the picture the nth input
channel influences the L output channel
through the M channel of the L filter
right it's uh
so
if I were to draw all influences every
input channel influences every output
aine map and all of these output aine
maps influence the divergence. So if I
were to focus on just one input map
because I want to compute the derivative
of the divergence with respect to figure
out how to compute the derivative of the
divergence with respect to this map
that has all of these influences. The
mth input channel
in influences
uh all of the output fine maps. So it
influences the nth output map through
the mth channel
of the nth filter. Right? L stands for
layer. So and this is the filter number
here. This is the filter number. This is
the input channel. So the mth input
channel
influences the nth output map through
the m channel of the nth filter. This
make sense to everybody
over here?
So I don't see a deal on the slide if I
do. Okay.
And so if I were to write the derivative
of the divergence with respect to this
guy, I would have to sum over all of the
output aphine maps. So the derivative of
the divergence with respect to the mth
input channel is the sum over all the
output aphine maps of the product of the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to the aphine map times the
derivative of the aphine map with
respect to the
uh input channel. So is this equation
making sense? We are summing over all of
the output channels and over all the
output channels we're summing the
product of the derivative for the aphine
map and the derivative of the aphine map
itself with respect to the channel.
Is this making sense to everybody?
I see
if okay. So the derivative of the
divergence with respect to this y sums
over all the aphine maps and the term it
sums is the product of the derivative of
the divergence with respect to the z
times the derivative of the z with
respect to y. That clear?
I'm assuming so. Okay.
So for this we have to figure out what
the derivative of a specific
output aphine map is with respect to the
input map. Specifically what we want to
know is what is the derivative of every
element of this aphine map with respect
to every element of the input map. These
are the derivatives we need to compute.
That clear to everybody?
I'm assuming I already have derivatives
for these guys. So for the chain rule to
work, I need to figure out what the
derivative of each of these elements is
with respect to each of these elements.
That make sense? Yes. No,
I see no responses. Okay, please respond
quickly guys. We have 250 slides to go
through. Okay, so let's see how this
works. to see how this works. Let's see
how the computation is done. Right? Now
consider this element of an input
channel. So let's say this guy, right?
That's being represented by this green
picture. And consider specifically this
element, the second row, second column.
How does it influence which of the
output elements does it influence? And
you can see that as you perform the
convolution,
this guy is used in the computation of a
bunch of output elements. Which are the
output elements this one influenced?
Anybody?
Which are the output elements this
element this highlighted element
influenced? Anyone
for six?
Only the first four, right? First two
rows, first two columns, right? So
more generally this guy influenced these
top four elements of every one of the
output I find maps right? Yes. No
over here. Okay.
So if I want to compute the derivative
of the divergence with respect to this
element, I would have to sum over all 16
of these guys. And the term I would have
to sum is the derivative of the
divergence with respect to each element
times the derivative of that element
with respect to this guy. This make
sense this equation.
I'm summing over all the maps. Within
each map, I'm summing over all the
elements influenced by this guy. and
over all the elements I'm summing the
product of the derivative of the
divergence with respect to the element
and times the derivative of that element
with respect to the y term that I'm
comput trying to compute the derivative
for so let's take a close look at this
what the we have these guys the term we
really want to compute is this one what
is say the derivative of this term with
respect to this guy how do I compute it
so let's take a look
To see how this works, we will first go
forwards.
So consider this to be the input channel
and this to be an output aine channel
map. Right? This is the filter. Now I'm
using two different ways of indexing the
filter. The filter is indexed by color.
It's also indexed by index value. So 0 0
is pink. 1 is yellow. Is this
illustration making sense that I have
two different ways of indexing the
filter? Because we'll use both.
Right. All right. So now if I place this
filter starting over here, which element
will I be computing on the output? If I
place the filter starting over here,
which element will I be computing on the
output? Anybody?
The 0 0 element. Right? So let's look at
this. I place the filter over here. I'm
computing the 0 0 element. But if I want
to compute the derivative for y22,
which filter element multiplied y22
and contributing to this guy, anybody?
I have a very helpful illustration. So
which filter element multiplied by 22 to
compute this guy 22. Right?
So we'll we'll get to that. Right? So
I have shown that by coloring this
orange. It means that in computing the
000 element I'm using the orange filter
element. And here is what the equation
says. Z00 plus equals because this is
just a individual contribution. Y22
time W22. Everybody okay with this
equation over here?
This making sense to everybody? Okay.
Now let me slide this one step forward
and compute Z 1 0. What happened? I now
place the filter on 1 0. So the filter
element that multiplied by 22 was now
W12.
Right? So is this equation making sense
over here? Okay. And so
then I move one more step forward.
Right? If I move one more step forward
now for Z20 I'm using W2.
For Z01
I'm using because I placed the filter
starting at 0 01 I'm using W21.
for Z11.
If I place the filter starting at 111,
I'm using the yellow filter filter
element which is W11. Right? So for this
guy, if I want to compute this one, I'd
be at least the filter starting here,
right? So which filter element would I
be using to compute this one, guys?
Which filter element would I be using to
compute this guy?
01. Right? Easy enough. And so that's
what happens, right? And so I keep doing
this. Do you guys notice a pattern as I
show you which filter element is used to
compute all these guys? Do you guys
notice a pattern in this equation?
Anybody?
Anybody notice a pattern?
What is the pattern? Flipped? No. What
is the pattern over here?
The sum of this index I've kept fixed,
right? because I'm trying to compute the
derivative for y22, right? The sum of
this index and this index is this guy.
Do you see that
everybody? You see that?
Yes. Right. And so I can actually say
that
to generalize
ZX prime Y prime equals plus= Y22 * W 2
- X prime 2 - Y prime because these two
index indices must sum to 22. This make
sense to everybody
over here this equation at the bottom.
And if I want to generalize it,
right? So
for any arbitrary element I can just say
zx prime y prime = yxy
plus wx - x prime y - y prime this
equation making sense the previous
example was for 22 but I can write it
for any xy right yes now okay so then
what is the derivative
of zx prime y prime with respect to yxy
what is the derivative of this this guy
with respect to this guy. Anyone?
What is this derivative?
Anybody?
Just this W element, right? That's it.
Easy. And so all I need to do is to say
the derivative of Z with respect to Y is
W Z dative of Z X prime Y prime with
respect to YXY is WX - X prime Y - Y
prime. And so when I wrote this equation
down the derivative of the divergence
with respect to this element. I'd be
summing in general over all elements of
all maps. So this is the sum over all
the output aine maps. This is the sum
over all output elements. the derivative
of the divergence with respect to the
element times the derivative of the
element with respect to y, the
corresponding y. And we know that the
derivative of this element with respect
to y is simply you know the derivative
of zx prime y prime with respect to yxy
is simply the weight x - x prime y - y
prime right I'm not mentioning the other
indices because we are always referring
to a specific input channel and a
specific output channel at a specific
layer. So is this equation making sense
to everybody? I just derived the entire
formula for this. This equation making
sense to everybody. Was it complicated?
Was that complicated?
Somebody say yes. Okay. It's not really
right. So
here is your sec. Okay. We don't have a
we records. Yeah.
X prime is any index of Z, right? We
have to sum over all the indices of Z.
So X prime and Y prime are the Z
indices. That answer your question.
Okay. So I'm giving you five seconds,
guys. These are this is an easy poll.
All right.
So, anybody want to answer the first
question? True or false?
First one, true or false?
Are you guys there?
Okay. And the second one, true or false?
Okay. So, both statements are true. To
compute the derivative at a single
aphine element y lmxy, we must compute
consider the contributions of every
position of every aphine map at the next
layer. And the derivative for a single
aphine element
not a activation element will require
summing over every position of every zap
in the next layer. Okay. So here is what
we have the derivative of the divergence
with respect to the xy element of the
mth input channel in the from the l
minus one layer sums over all n output
channels over all output channels it's
summing over all positions and at each
position you're summing the term you're
summing is the product of the divergence
with respect to the element of the
output activation map at that position
times
the filter value
at X - X prime Y - Y prime right so why
one cell of Z is only influencing one
cell of Y right no so
once
if I look at this this cell of Z is
going to be influenced by all the Y's
but we looking at a specific Y
and a specific Y is going to influence a
specific Z. There's only one there's
only one connection between any any Y
element and any Z element. Right? So,
but then this is actually just a
convolution.
It looks like a complicated equation,
but it's much much simpler than that. To
see how, let's look at what happens,
right? When I compute this formula,
I'm going to see what happens. So, if I
want to compute the derivative for say
y22, right? I'm just going to plug in
this formula. the derivative of the
divergence at xrime yprime with respect
to zx prime y prime time w x - y x prime
y - y prime right so so
for y22 I'm multiplying the derivative
for z 0 so x prime is 0 y prime is 0
which means x - x prime y - y prime is
just xy right and in my example x and y
are 22 right so the derivative of y22 is
the derivative
at Z 0 time W22 as shown by the orange.
Is this making sense
what we've got here? Just this equation.
Okay.
And then plus the derivative at 1 0 *
W12
plus the derivative at 2 0 * the weight
that was used in computing it, right?
which is w2
plus the derivative at 01 times the
weight that was used in computing it
which is
uh which is w21 right plus
the derivative at 1 1 * the weight that
was used in computing it which was w11
plus the derivative at 21 times the
weight that was used in computing it
which is w1
so did this equation make sense how I
just generated this plot. I'm showing
you the filter value index of the filter
value through colors for every filter
element that multiply the corresponding
the underlying Z derivative to give you
the derivative for Y22. So is this
making sense all of you guys?
Okay. Do you see a pattern?
Do you see a pattern? What happened?
What's the pattern you see? Anybody?
What is the pattern you see? What is the
relationship of this picture to this
picture?
Rotated.
The filter is flipped. So what we did
was we flipped this filter top to
bottom, left to right. So we were trying
to compute the derivative at y22. So we
flipped the filter, you know, top to
bottom, left to right, and positioned it
so that the 000 element sat on top of
22.
And then you sum this up, right? We put
the flip filter on top of the Z
derivative map and then summed it up.
Do you guys see that?
Right. This is what we did. We flipped
the filter, sat the filter,
flip filter sitting on top of two with
with the 000 element on top of 22 and
then computed an inner product and that
gave me the derivative for 22. Make
sense to everybody?
You guys see this? Yes.
Okay. Or more generally, if I want a
derivative for yxy,
what I do is flip this filter,
place the filter such that the 000
element is sitting on the xy element of
the z derivative map and then compute an
inner product. So is this equation
making sense to you guys from the
picture? Is this making making sense?
Yes or no?
Yes. No. Guys,
I'm going to see just a few yeses.
Can I have a little more enthusiasm,
please?
All right. And so, but then
top to left to right, top to bottom,
Jesse, as you can see by comparing these
two pictures, right? This orange went to
the top. This 001 came to the bottom,
right? But then
right this is the derivative of
we just took this filter
we flipped it left to right top to
bottom but then we zero padded this this
is the der map of the derivatives with
respect to z but then we zero padded it
with k minus one rows and column columns
of zeros. Why? Because if this was
originally of size m and the filter was
of size k then what was this size? If
the input map was size m and the filter
was size k what was this size?
What do we get
over here?
This was going to be m minus k + 1.
Right?
Now if I if I pad it on both sides with
k minus one rows and k minus one zeros.
Now what is the final size?
What is the final size? It's going to be
m - k + 1 + k - one. So that will cancel
out + k - one. Right? So it's going to
become m + k minus one. Right?
Yes or no?
Now if I convolve this guy
with this flipped filter which is k
cross k what is the size of the
derivative
if I convolve this guy the zero parent
one with k cross k what is the size of
the derivative
anybody
it's going to be n plus k minus one
but then you're going to lose my
you know minus k minus one. So these
will get cancelceled out. You're left
with n, right? And so here's a fantastic
rule that you must remember. If you have
an input of some size whatever I'll call
this, right? Going through a process and
then out comes a scaler in which case
it's a divergence. The derivative of the
divergence with respect to the input to
this process will be the same size as
the as the original input itself. That
always holds. And so you can see that
when I zero pad it. And then if I were
to convolve this guy,
zero padded guy with this flip filter
like so.
The result is going to be a picture
which is exactly the same size as the
input. Do you guys see that?
Yes or no?
Right. And so what happened over here?
this business that I just showed you
when I flip the filter and set it at XY
the overall process is like so I'm going
to zero pad the Z derivative map with K
minus one rows and zeros on every side
flip my filter and then just simply
convolve this with my flip filter and
that's going to give me the derivative
or the contribution of one Zmap to the
derivative to the of the corresponding
input channel but then the input each
input channel influences the divergence
through all of the Zmaps. Right? So to
compute the derivative of the divergence
with respect to this guy, we must sum
over all of them or more explicitly over
all elements of all of the Zmaps. So how
does that work? We wrote out the math,
but then if you stick in the math over
here, here's what you're going to do. I
want the derivative of the divergence
with respect to say this map. So this
map is going to be influencing all of
the output
aine maps. The mth input channel is
going to be influencing all of the
output channels through the mth channel
of all the filters. So you're going to
pick the mth channel of all the filters
and then this so these are the mth
channel of all filters. This is you have
as many of these elements as the number
of output aphine maps. You would flip
all of these guys. Then you would zero
pad all of the derivative maps for the
output fine maps on both sides. And then
this flip filter is simply going to
convolve
the zero padded guys on top. And that's
going to give you the derivative for the
filter the derivative for the input fi
map. That make sense to everybody the
process?
Yes. No.
Right. And do you also see why we got
that? Where we got that from?
Right. Okay.
Can I have a few more thumbs ups? I have
a very anemic one. Thumbs up.
Two seven like there are 200 people in
class. People must be awake, right? So
you No, you have to you have to flip it.
That's the math. There's no there's no
choice of not flipping. Okay.
So, here is the overall nice little you
know animation showing you how the
derivative is computed.
All right.
And so we now we continue. So you zero
pad it and you continue to compute
elements for the derivative map as long
as the flip filter has at least one
element in the unpadded non-zero nonzero
for the unpadded Zmap derivatives and we
saw that if you work through the math
that's math that's going to give you a
derivative of the size of the input
itself. So the sizes work out
which means that if the Z Y map Y map
was zero padded in the forward pass the
derivative map will be the size of the
zero padded map and then you're going to
have to throw away the zero zero pad
regions because what you really want is
just the derivative of the original map
itself.
So questions. Yes.
5 seconds, guys. 10 seconds. 10 seconds.
Okay, let me end this poll.
Can you tell me which statements are
true?
Which ones are true?
One and four.
To compute the der top three, right? So
to compute the derivative with respect
to the M activation map of the L
convolution layer, you must select the M
channels of all the
E layer filters. I'm sorry. So
the L layer filters right the filters
must be flipped left right up down and
they must convolve the derivative maps.
Okay, sorry. To compute the derivatives
for the L layer, we must start at the
L+1 layer. So, we must select the M
channels of all the L +1 layer filters.
They must be flipped left, right, and
up, down. And then they must convolve
the derivative maps for the L+1 layer
aine values. Right? So, everybody okay
with this? I'm assuming most of you got
it.
And so the overall
uh
computation for algorithm for computing
the derivative with respect to y l minus
one. You're computing this using the
formula that we just saw. But this
formula instead of implementing this
formula blindly using loops. You can do
this using convolution with a flipped
filter. Right? So I have a pseudo code
for this. I'm going to skip the pseudo
code.
Can I assume now or am I being
optimistic if I assume that this has
been understood?
Can I assume that this has been
understood?
Can I get some yeses, some thumbs ups
and not very anemic number of thumbs
ups? So like 25 I think is a healthy
number.
You disappoint me guys. It stopped at
18.
That's I was hoping for 25. You stopped
at 18. Guys, wake up. I'm putting some
effort into this. Thank you.
So the third thing we are left with is
how to compute the derivative with
respect to the filters. Right? So
let's see how we do this. Again, we have
to consider all influences.
And so consider this filter. This is
some really bad animation because
mattplot lib is disgusting in changing
the color maps continuously as it draws
plots. But consider say the central
element of this filter.
You you can see that when it when you're
computing an aphine map this central
element of the filter is used in the
computation of every one of the output
aphine values. Can you see that over
here as the filter scans?
Yes. No.
Okay. So that's a single. Yes.
And so I want to basically what happens
is that each filter element
over here
is going to be influencing just one
output aine map because a filter only is
used only in the computation of a single
output aine map. Moreover,
each filter element comes from one
specific channel of the filter. So, it's
only going to invoke the corresponding
channel of the input. So, let's see how
this works out. Right? So, these yellow
patches are representing the input
channels. This is the output channel.
And now, if I want to figure out which
output elements this filter element
influences,
this is filter element. If I use zero
index, it's 1 two, right? So the filter
element one two multiplies
y12 to compute z z00 0. And there are
some additional you know additive terms.
Is this making sense to you guys? Do you
see this
filter element one two right? So now
it multiplies
y 22
to compute
z element 1 0. Do you guys see that too?
If I place this at 1 0, it computes z 1
0. But the filter element itself
multiplies by 22. Right? Yes. No. Okay.
And then it multiplies
in computing z20. It multiplies by 32
and so on. Right. Do you see a pattern?
Do you see a pattern
over here?
Yes or no?
Do you see a pattern?
What is the pattern? Okay. What's the
pattern over here?
Once again, you're going to find that
ZXY the index these two indices
always sum to give you this index.
Right?
Check down the column.
So zxy
in if you if you see the contribution of
w12 to zy that comes through yx + 1
y y + 2 I'm using this y twice but I
don't think it causes much confusion. So
do you see this equation over here?
Yes. Can you guys see this? Right. Can
you generalize this equation to any wig?
How would you generalize this to WIG?
What would it be?
What what is the term here going to be?
Anyone?
What will it be? Just generalizing this
X plus I Y + J. Right? Easy. And so
that's what you have. ZXY
is got some additive terms. But the
contribution of the ig filter element is
through my x + i y + j. So what is the
derivative of zxy with respect to wig?
Again, what is this guy?
The derivative of zxy with respect to
wig. What is it?
It's on the screen. So you should be
able to read it, guys.
Someone read it out to for me please.
It's just y.
It's going to be come on. It's y x + i y
+ j is it not? I've written it out.
So
and so using this formula right here, if
I want to compute the derivative of the
divergence with respect to any
particular weight element of the filter,
I'd have to sum sum over all of the
elements. So a filter the nth filter the
the
mth channel of the nth filter only
invokes the mth input channel and the
nth output channel. Right? So the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to say wig is going to be the
respect is going to sum over all
elements of the output fine map and the
term it sums is the derivative of the
divergence with respect to zxy time zy
derivative of zxy with respect to y of
wigj and this term of course this
already computed if you were performing
back prop and this guy we just saw the
derivative of zxy with respect to wiggy
x + i y + j. So I can just plug it in
here. And so this equation will give us
the derivative for the
for the uh filter. Right? So is this
equations clear to all of you guys? This
making sense to everybody?
Yes or no?
Okay. Does this look like a convolution
also?
The answer should be yes. Why? I'm just
plugging the equation right here. Okay,
just for your reference. So the
derivative with respect to wig,
it's summing over all elements. Okay,
and with you're summing the derivative
for each xy
by y + i y + j. So if I want the
derivative for W12,
it's like placing this map because I'm I
have this plus I + J, right? It's like
placing this map at the one two position
of the input channel and then performing
an inner product. Do you see this? See
what I just did over here?
Yes. No.
Just similarly if I want the derivative
for w 0 0 so this is 0 0 right then
these are going to go away it's like
placing this derivative map on starting
from the 0 0 position of the input and
then computing an inner product
so does that give you an idea of what's
going on so here just look at this
equation again right to compute the
derivative of say w12
using this formula
So I summed over all the Z elements,
right?
But each Z element was multiplied by a Y
element and the Y element was X + I, Y +
J. So it's like saying I'm putting Z 0
at I J. It's like putting 01 at I + 1, I
+ 0, J + 1 and so on. So I basically
place this map starting at the J
position and summed it up. I'm showing
you two examples for IG12 and IG00
that answer right and so that tells you
what's happening
this guy can be computed the derivative
for the filters can be directly computed
from the formula but it's just a
convolution how is that just give me a
second
okay
if I want to compute the derivative
Look the
IAT channel input channel influences the
J output channel
where with through the IAT channel of
the J filter right. So the second input
channel will influence the first output
channel through the second channel of
the first filter. So to compute the
derivative for this guy I just need to
consider these two. The rest of them are
not involved. And so I would I place the
derivative map for this output
on the input channel and then just
convolve. And if you do this, the output
derivative is going to be the derivative
for the corresponding channel of the
corresponding filter. This make sense to
everybody?
Yes or no?
Right. And you can see the sizes work
out. How do the sizes work out? Again,
if the input,
let's say, if the input is size M and
the filter is size K, what is the output
size going to be over here?
I won't wait for you. It's n plus k
minus one, right? N minus k + one.
Sorry, thank you.
I did manage to not wait for you and
make a mistake, but it's going to be m
minus k + one. So if I convolve this
musk +1 entry with this m entry, if I
convolve this these two, what is the
result going to be in size?
What is the result going to be?
It's going to be m minus
m - k + 1
- 1. Right?
So these will cancel out. This cancels
out and the result is going to be K.
That make sense to everybody?
Everyone, right? And so you see that the
filter size derivative also works out.
And so the filter derivatives because
you already know the derivatives for all
the Z's. To compute the derivative for
any map for any filter, you just take
the corresponding Zmap and then cor
the derivatives to the corresponding
Zmap and convolve the the input channel
to give you the derivative for the
filter.
So because an input channel is going to
be uh
you know because an output channel is
going to be computed from all the input
channels. So if you want the derivative
of the entire filter all you would do is
convolve every one of these guys with
the derivative map for the output aphine
map and that's going to give you the
derivative for the entire filter. So,
did all of this make sense?
Yes or no?
This makes sense to everybody.
Can I have a few more thumbs ups before
I move on?
Guys, you guys aren't very enthusiastic.
You have to be.
Okay. So, 25. Thank you. I keep moving
on. All right. So, this is our fourth
poll. TS, can you please pull up the
fourth poll?
15 seconds, guys.
5 seconds.
All right. Which ones are true?
So which ones are true guys?
Just one. You don't flip. Right? Did we
ever flip over here? We never flipped
anything. Correct?
To compute the derivative for the input
channels, we had to flip the filter. But
when you're computing the channel
derivative for the filter, there is no
flipping. You just directly uh convolve.
That make sense to everybody? Everybody
good with that? Yes. No. Some thumbs
ups, thumbs downs, whatever.
Okay.
10. I'll wait for a count of 25.
So 16.
Humor me. Okay. 20. Okay. We got that.
So I have some pseudo code for it. I'll
uh uh skip the pseudo code. Right. But
there's something very interesting that
you can see. We went through a lot of
effort but then it turns out that you
can be lazy and not learn the math and
not learn the diagonals, never see
anything and just work through code if
you know how back propagation and
derivative rules work for any
computation of the form which is y=
sigma of z. The loss derivative is dl /
dz simply dl / dy * sigma prime z.
Right? We know this. Similarly, if you
have any computation in the forward pass
where Z= WY, then DL / DY + C= W DL / DZ
and DL / DW is Y * DL / DZ. So these two
formula make sense, right? These guys
make sense?
Yes. No. Okay. So all you need to do it
turns out is to go back into your code
and so in the forward pass if you're
going left to right and you're going
through the code in a particular manner
I just rewrite the code except that all
the indices are now going to go
downwards from going going from one to W
is going to go down from W to one right
then in the innermost pass or in the
innermost loop we just did Z plus= WY
And then once you computed everything,
we applied an activation to it. Right?
So instead what I will do is go back and
move this on top of the loop and say
again this is y is activation applied to
z. So the derivative with respect to z
is the derivative with respect to y
times the derivative of the activation.
And then because going forward we had z=
w we had z= wy right so going backwards
the derivative for y plus= w * dz and
the derivative for w += y * dz right
going backwards here we got the
derivative for z. So this is telling us
how to apply the rule for this guy to
get the derivative for y and w. It's
very straightforward. May not be very
clear right now because I don't have
time to go through it in detail. But go
through the slides and it's very
interesting how you don't really have to
worry about
figuring out derivative rules. If you
just look at the code, you can
manipulate the code to compute
derivatives. Right?
So
we can assume right now that we have
managed to figure out how to compute the
derivatives to
how to compute the derivatives for the
input
channels from the derivatives for the
output activation maps and also the
derivatives for the filters. And without
asking you guys, I'm going to assume
we're good with all of this.
So the next thing we have to Okay, this
is done, right? The next thing we have
to worry about is
pooling layers. How do you compute the
derivative of the input to a pooling
layer from the derivative of the output?
Now, what do pooling layers do? Pooling
layers pull groups of values to reduce
jitter sensitivity. Right? They scan
with a pooling filter. The most common
pooling is max pooling. You look over a
small window, pick the largest value,
right? If these guys were 1 63 1 3 6 and
5, the largest value is six. You're just
going to copy that six over. Now my
question is this. When you're going
backwards, I'm assuming that you already
have the derivative
for this guy. Right? Now
answer me this. If I perturb this
element,
will this will that perturb this guy?
Yes or no?
So what is the derivative of this
element with respect to one? This this
entry
derivative zero. What if I perturb this
guy?
What is the derivative? Um this one
perturbing this guy will not change the
output. So this derivative should also
be zero. Right? Yes. No.
Right.
Yeah. So perturbing it infinite
decimally. So what about this one?
If I perturb it, does it change the
output?
So the derivative for the output with
respect to this element is going to be
what is it going to be? One. Okay,
that's the basic rule. Which is why when
we perform max pooling in the forward
pass, we stored the location of the
largest value and then copied the value
over. And this is what we did when we
were going forward. Right? When you're
going backwards, we take advantage of
the fact that
only the element that was largest
influence the output. And so since while
going backwards, you already have the
derivative over here. The derivative at
the input to the pooling, you can just
copy this guy over to the location of
the largest and these are going to get
zero. So the derivative with respect to
y kl
equals the derivative you know
kl the k position of the input of the
pulley is the same as the derivative
with respect to the ig element of the
output of the pulley if this kl was the
index that was copied over and zero
otherwise. Right? So, did this whole
principle make sense over here
through my scribbled picture? Did this
make sense?
You just copy this over, right?
Okay. Can I get a few more yeses,
thumbs ups,
waves?
Okay,
I've become less greedious, you know,
except 15. So in the forward pass we had
the first store the when you were doing
max pooling we stored the position of
the largest and then copied the largest
value over in the backward pass we just
copy the value over to the position of
the largest. Now why am I using plus
equals over here? Anybody? Why am I
using plus equals?
Anyone?
Why am I using plus equals over here?
Because it's a sum.
Anybody else? It's a max pooling. There
is no sum. Right. Next step, someone
else.
So
what would happen here is if I'm
performing max pooling, right? So if I
were sliding by say so let's say I'm
stepping forward by just one and so then
let's say this guy is the maximum
element
going forward so then this guy is going
to get copied over here right then let's
say I stride by one and this guy remains
the maximum element so the same guy is
also going to get copied over here right
this make sense to everybody
that a maximum element could be the max
in multiple windows. And so when you go
backwards, all of these derivatives are
going to get summed up to get the the
derivative out here. Which is why we
have a
plus equals in the pseudo code.
Is that clear to everybody?
Yes. No.
Okay. Can I see some thumbs ups again?
All right.
So,
the other is mean pooling. When I
perform mean pooling,
then I'm taking the average of all of
these guys and copying them over. Right
now, going backwards,
I have the derivative
over here.
How will this derivative get copied
back? I'll get passed back anybody. How
is it going to get passed back?
What happens
like softmax?
This is the average of all of the guys
going in, right? It's just going to be
distributed uniformly over all of these
elements, is it not?
Just look at this formula here, right?
So this is this divided by 4 plus this
divided by 4 plus this divided 4 plus
this divided by 4. So each one was
multiplied by 1 / 4 and then they were
all sum to give you this guy. So when
you go back this element is going to get
distributed backwards to all four with
weight 1 / k².
This make sense to everyone?
No.
Okay.
So I evet where did I lose you?
K squ because this is K and this is K.
So 2 + 2 that answer you
right?
Okay. And so here is the pseudo code.
When you're going forward, you just
compute the mean of the window.
when it's going you're going backwards
the the derivative at any element
is distributed uniformly
over all of the the entire region that
was used in computing this this element.
Why am I doing a plus equals again over
here?
Why do we have a plus equals
anyone?
to account for overlapping windows,
right? Perfect.
And so
we've seen how to compute every uh the
derivative for every element of the
network. So going forward, the input
would go into the network. It goes
through the entire network and then you
get an output.
Then you can compute the divergence with
respect to the desired output.
And then you can perform backdrop using
the standard MLP backdrop rules to get
the derivatives here. Fold those
derivatives back into these channels and
then use the rules that we just saw to
pass those derivatives backward through
pooling and convolution layers to
compute both the derivatives of the
input to each operation and also the
filters themselves. And eventually of
course you can also get the derivatives
for the input to the network itself. Any
questions? Did all of this make sense?
We have a few minutes. I finished 3
minutes early. Did all of this make
sense? Any questions?
So,
so the CNN is a supervised version of
the of a computational model of the
vision. It includes convolution layers
comprising learned filters that scan the
outputs of the previous layer followed
by an activation and pooling layers that
operate over groups of outputs from the
convolution layer for jitter and
variance. You can have optional resizing
operations typically performed with
strides greater than one for
downsampling or interpolation of zeros
for upsampling. The parameters of the
network can be learned through regular
gradient descent where gradients are
computed using back propagation. So
computing derivatives for convolution
layers is simply also a convolution
operation. You convolve transposed
filters with derivative maps of the
output for derivatives of input maps.
And then you convolve the input maps
with the derivative maps of the output
for the derivatives of filters.
Back prop of pooling operations
redistributes the derivatives of the
output and the output over all the
inputs that actively contributed to it.
So this is a very succent way of uh
summar summarizing what what the back
propagation rules for cooling layers
are. So we'll stop right here. That's
the end of this lecture. I'll wait a
couple of minutes for questions and then
first did the lecture make sense to
everybody
and we'll answer that next class because
we have not addressed upsampling and
downsampling so far. Right? So,
okay, give me since the class is over,
I'll wait for 30 thumbs ups and then we
can and wait for any questions.
Oh, wow. We got 30. Fantastic.
Uh, all right. Any other any questions,
guys?
If not, let me stop the recording and
thank you all very much for